早安,我們現在是聖誕的時間
就會有一個Advent Series
Advent是耶穌 is coming
Jesus is coming
And we are waiting for his coming
有沒有人記得上個星期有兩個家庭
有兩個媽媽是誰呢?
有沒有人記得?
Who are the two mothers?
兩個媽媽是誰?
Elizabeth and Mary
Elizabeth是誰來的?
Describe her
她是很年輕,她很老
誰覺得她是很年輕的?舉手
Ok,一個
誰覺得她是很老的?
對,她是很老的
接著瑪麗亞呢?
瑪麗亞你猜一下她是多少歲?
十幾
有沒有人十三到十七歲的?舉手
有沒有女生十三到十七歲的?
你還舉手
Ok
Are you ready to be a mother if you are 13 to 17?
That is Mary
Ok,我們看下一個頁
有兩個家庭
Two unexpected births
第一是Elizabeth
她很大年紀了
她的家庭是侍奉神的
她的寺廟是侍奉神的
但很多年都沒有小孩
那些人就覺得
你沒有小孩?
你做了什麼?有什麼錯?
What's wrong with you?
你有什麼問題?
為什麼沒有子女?
Something must be wrong with you
你得罪神了,有什麼?
是不是?
那她就可能有很ashamed
Right?
Very ashamed
但是Gabriel
不是這個Gabriel
是Angel Gabriel
就跟他說
是不是?
Zechariah說
God will bless you with a son
And his name will be
他的兒子會叫什麼名字?
John
是不是?
是不是Gospel of John的John?
不是,不是Disciple John
We'll see later which John
但是Zechariah信不信?
信不信Gabriel?
不信,是不是?
那他就怎樣?
神就
mute了他的mouth
他啞了,是不是?
It also said
that the Holy Spirit will be filling
this child before he is born
聖靈會充滿
John the Baptist
before he is born
OK,瑪利亞呢?
瑪利亞
So the opposite
OK
Elizabeth很老
沒有子女
Mary呢?
是什麼來的?
Mary is a virgin
還沒結婚
She is engaged to 誰?
engaged to 誰?
Joseph
對,engaged to Joseph
Gabriel also appeared to her
and said
耶穌
will become
the child
that will save the world
瑪利亞就信神
信Gabriel說
然後我們看到
聖靈是充滿
他的womb
to conceive of Jesus Christ
OK, that was last week's lesson
這個星期我們會看
這三個父母
他們的response是什麼?
是Elizabeth
Mary
和Zechariah
Elizabeth
and Zechariah
OK, 我們一起讀
Luke Chapter 1
OK
瑪利亞一聽到
天使Gabriel說
她就去了哪裡?
她就去了她的
是不是cousin?
sister? cousin?
What is it?
她的cousin
OK
cousin
yeah, cousin
OK
然後她一看到
Elizabeth的時候
Mary一看到Elizabeth的時候
那又怎樣?
她的肚子
leapt for joy
the baby in her womb
今天問問媽媽
有媽媽的舉手
Mothers, raise your hand
OK
你為什麼舉Uncle Stanley的手?
媽媽舉手
你們懷孕的時候
有沒有感覺到
Baby會有震動?
有什麼時候會很興奮?
有沒有什麼情況會很興奮?
有沒有?
那些媽媽
沒有?
是很隨機的?
是不是很隨機?
很隨機的
OK
你可以睡覺
然後Baby很興奮
可以的?
Wow, OK
這個是很特別的
因為
Spirit
The Holy Spirit
filled Elizabeth
and this baby
是不是
It's a supernatural thing
因為是Miracle來的
是不是
這個
你的Baby
怎麼會認識到
第二個Baby的?
It's a miracle
OK
是因為聖靈去充滿
John the Baptist
And John the Baptist
was so excited to see Jesus
你有沒有一些好朋友
你很久沒見過
然後你一見到他
You're so excited
So excited
是不是
這個是Baby John的反應
他見到耶穌
哇,好久沒見了
Actually, they've never met
Right?
Technically, they've never met
Because John the Baptist never existed
這個第一次見面
The Savior of the world
可能John的眼睛、耳朵、嘴巴、鼻子
可能都還沒完全發展
但是聖靈充滿了他
OK
Mary
記不記得
我們剛才說
她大概幾歲?
13到17歲
是不是
In her teen years
她那時候還沒結婚
是不是
她還沒結婚
所以她懷孕了
還沒結婚
那些人會覺得她怎樣
會覺得她怎樣
Adultery
Right?
Having sex before marriage
是不是
會很羞恥的
那時候
是不是
很羞恥
還有
如果你是
engaged to 這個女生
你會覺得怎樣
Gabriel
你engaged to 這個女生
已經懷孕了
你會覺得怎樣
Yeah
Very disrespectful
你跟了哪個男人一起
是不是
You'll be so ashamed
但是
但是Mary
went to Elizabeth
因為她知道Elizabeth
would understand her situation
Elizabeth would understand her situation
OK
我們看到
Elizabeth was filled with the Holy Spirit
聖靈充滿她的心
是不是
然後她說什麼
Blessed are you among women
她Blessed瑪利亞
是不是
她不是說
你跟哪個男人一起
你都沒結婚
搞錯啊
你做什麼
How will Joseph
How will Gabriel feel
是不是
How will Joseph feel
她不是這樣說
不是
因為聖靈充滿她
她給她有understanding
of the situation
她要給她有
supernatural revelation
of the situation
她是知道
不是一個curse
這個是一個blessing
這個是一個blessing來的
瑪利亞是被聖靈充滿
and she conceives of the Spirit
of the Holy
Holy Savior of God
去充滿
with full of the Holy Spirit
Right
conceive Jesus Christ
還有
她什麼
不是單是bless她
她是elevate她
人們會look down on Mary
是不是
但她elevate her
Blessed are you among women
全世界的女人
Blessed are you
差不多最Blessed
Why
Because she has the privilege
of carrying the Savior of the world
She blesses Mary
and on top of that
what does she say
Blessed is she
who believe that the Lord
would fulfill His promise
The mother of the Lord
should come to me
是不是
她認識
這個BB
瑪利亞的BB
是誰
是主耶穌
是我們的救主
Elizabeth recognizes
the Lord that Mary carries
我們看到
有三樣東西
聖靈是帶什麼
帶喜樂
在這個situation
這個situation是可以很shameful的
瑪利亞可以go into hiding
是不是
她懷孕未結婚
She could go into hiding
But she does not
她去找誰
她去找Elizabeth
因為她知道
Elizabeth都被聖靈充滿
And so
the Holy Spirit brings joy
Revelation
聖靈幫他們認識
這個是救主
主耶穌是救主
祂是神
是不是
還有recognition
recognition that Mary is blessed
And lastly
She reinforces and encourages Mary
The Holy Spirit brings joy
我們真的跟隨聖靈
那時祂會帶喜樂
在我們的團契那裡
那麼
我們這個explorer
我們有沒有被聖靈充滿
Have we been filled with the Holy Spirit here
in explorer
如果我們有呢
我們這個團契
我們這個congregation
有沒有喜樂
有沒有joy
Do we have joy
Because
Holy Spirit brought joy
to Mary and Elizabeth
And they had fellowship together
Two households
coming together
They had joy
If we follow the Holy Spirit here in explorer
We will have the joy of Christ also
我們去年去了camp
好玩嗎
我們有不同的比賽
有debate
又有那個
什麼scavenger hunt
很有喜樂
We need to bring that joy
to this congregation
as we follow the Holy Spirit
OK
Let's continue to read
我們看了Elizabeth的反應
我們現在看瑪利亞的反應
OK
Let's read English together
這個
這個song
是叫Mary's Magnificent
因為第三個字
是My soul magnifies the Lord
My soul magnifies the Lord
我們看到
瑪利亞的反應是什麼
第一
她是敬拜神
她說什麼
My soul magnifies the Lord
magnify
是什麼
中文是什麼
這個magnify
OK
她是
see the Lord as the most important thing
是嗎
有沒有人在科學課
用一個magnifying glass
有沒有
有沒有人
記不記得
你用magnifying glass
是看什麼的
去zoom in
是不是
不是我們的
online zoom in
這個magnifying glass
你是想zoom in
在一些東西很小的
It could be a bug
It could be a splinter in your nail
你有刺的時候
你用一個magnifying glass
去看到刺在哪裡
然後才可以拿出來
Mary現在是怎樣
她是magnify the Lord
神在她的生命中是最大的
God is the biggest in her life
她是magnify the Lord
她是敬拜神
是嗎
她說
magnify the Lord
她的spirit rejoices
還有她是怎樣
她是謙卑她自己
I am the servant of the Lord
第一
她是敬拜神
第二
她說的那些
她唱的那些
是充滿什麼
Scripture
The word
第二個w
是word
她是怎樣說的
She sings of God's character
His mercy
His strength
His holiness
His faithfulness
是不是
全部
是神的characteristic來的
She understands who God is
你看看這個年輕人
13到17歲
他是認識神的說話
She sings about God's word
他是敬拜神
他謙卑他自己
我們這裡有沒有好像瑪利亞一樣
Teenager
但是呢
願意去謙卑他自己
去敬拜神
去magnify the Lord
Mary is an amazing example
她不是說
哎呀神啊
你為什麼
差遣我
不用了
我很害怕
我要讀書
我很忙
我要打球
我要打遊戲
不是
她是怎樣
她是謙卑她自己
她說神你想我做什麼
我就會做什麼
我們今天在explore
我們有沒有
好像瑪利亞一樣的teenager
願意去謙卑跟隨
侍奉神呢
Do we have Mary's in this congregation
Do we
That are willing to follow Jesus Christ
Follow the Lord's calling
第三
我們看到
他有world mission的心態
Next slide
我們看到Mary是有
world mission的心態
我們怎樣看到她有world mission的心態呢
她唱什麼
He has scattered the proud
brought down the mighty
exalted the humble estate
filled the hungry
sent the rich away empty
她是唱什麼
她是唱耶穌將來會做什麼
He has come to humble the proud
to humble the proud
He has come to bring up the lowly
耶穌是跟誰吃飯
是不是跟很有錢的人
只是跟很有錢的人
不是
他是跟tax collector
跟sinner去吃飯
他跟prostitute去聊天
他給prostitute
put perfume on his body
他不是單止跟很有錢
很有權威的人去聊天
No
He is out there to seek and save the lost
瑪利亞給聖靈充滿的時候
她是認識神的工作是什麼
祂的mission是什麼
God's mission is to save the world
save the world
所以我們看到
Mary的example
it's a wonderful example for us today
it's a wonderful example for you as young people
to follow the Lord
去謙卑自己
侍奉神
讀聖經
我們的mission是讀聖經
是不是
侍奉神
傳福音
That's our mission
and that was Mary's mission also
我們看到在她的song
Now we see
next slide
that Mary worshipped the Lord
Mary exalted God
Mary is not
Mary is not God
OK 有些天主教的時候
他們是worship Mary的
給她有divine status
但我們看到這裡是很清楚
瑪利亞是敬拜神的
She is worshipping God
She is giving praise to God
她不是叫人worship我
pray to me
因為我也有power
No, she does not do that
所以我們不是去idolize Mary
我們是認識她是humble
謙卑她自己
去侍奉神
And so we need to give her credit
that she was a faithful servant of God
Not somebody that we pray to
or we give divine power to
And so we see
聖靈是align我們的heart
next slide
聖靈會align我們的heart
to worship the Lord
敬拜神
會認識神的話語
understand the word of God
和認識神的mission是什麼
她去save the world
She is here to save the world
OK, now it is time for discussion
Mary is full of worship
the word and mission minded towards the world
How can you be more like Mary
你怎麼可以become more like Mary today
第二個question
Elizabeth brought community
a community of joy
through the Holy Spirit
How can you be more like Elizabeth
to develop a joyful community
in Explorer
OK, mentor
我們現在和我們的students
let's have a discussion together
有五分鐘
OK, how is your discussion
有沒有人想分享
有沒有人有什麼組想分享
聽一下那些女生
那些女生
那些女生有什麼想分享
有沒有
沒有
OK,那些男生
有沒有人
Uncle Stanley你的組有沒有人想分享
OK, Jasper
Jasper你分享一下
How can you be more like Mary
OK,我們聽一下Jasper怎麼說
Read your Bible
OK, read your Bible
Very good
有沒有人開始讀聖經
有沒有開始讀聖經
OK, very good
Two people
OK,還有呢
Sam你的組有沒有人想分享
Rico
Rico有沒有人想分享
你覺得你怎麼可以
become more like Mary
Don't know
OK, Sam你幫他summarize一下
你的組有什麼要說
他們summarize的問題是
他們以為自己要變女生
假裝
他們會更像伊麗莎白
他們覺得要變女生
OK, that is not the lesson for today
OK, that is not the lesson
(笑)
Oh, sorry
OK,我們看了Elizabeth
接著我們看了Mary的例子
第三呢
我們會看Zachariah的例子
Elizabeth bore John
OK, Elizabeth's baby's name was John
以前他們是多數會
她給Baby
Baby的名字
Baby
Baby的名字是會
sort of follow the father's side
Zachariah呢
就
記不記得他是
他是什麼
他是Mew左
是不是
記不記得他是Mew左
知不知道為什麼他是Mew左呢
是因為
The story is
在那個Temple
每年有一次
是有incense offering的
每年有一次是incense offering
那他們會
他會
buy lots
OK
他會抽人
抽一個priest進去
去make the special offering
因為他是represent誰
他是represent
以色列
那些以色列人
去go and pray to the lord
OK
into the temple
the holy of holies
這是一個很special的moment來的
OK
是很privilege
the priest才可以做這個事
所以好像
香港選你去奧運的時候
OK
That is like
the example
那Zachariah進了Temple的時候
他燒這個offering的時候
然後怎樣
Angel Gabriel appeared to him
and told him about
his baby John
那Zachariah就不相信了
那出來的時候
平時他會祈禱
他出來的時候
他會bless the people
God has heard your prayer
God will bless you
是不是
他就會可能說這個blessing
May the lord bless you and keep you
and make his face shine upon you
是不是
那個priest
一offering
完了這個offering
出來的時候
他會有這個benediction
但是他出來的時候
他是什麼
他是啞了
是不是
那所以
Let's continue to read
Next slide
Let's read the English together
1, 2, 3
Then they made signs to his father
to find out what he would like
to name the child
He asked for a writing tablet
my iPad
我的iPad
And to everyone's astonishment
he wrote
His name is John
Immediately his mouth was opened
and his tongue set free
And he began to speak
Praising God
All the neighbors were filled with awe
And throughout the hills
country of Judea
were talking about all these things
Everyone who heard
wondered about it
Asking
What then is this child going to be
For the lord's hand was with him
OK
他一出來的時候
他是啞了
是不是
但是他去proclaim
and prophesied
this new blessing
這個新的blessing
所以
他的song
是叫做
Zacharias Benedictus
這個新的blessing
Let's read the new blessing together
Next slide
OK
1, 2, 3
His father Zacharias
was filled with the Holy Spirit
and prophesied
Praise be to the Lord
the God of Israel
because he has come to his people
and redeemed them
He has raised up the horn of salvation
for us
the house of servant David
as he has
through the holy prophets
of long ago
salvation from our enemies
and from the hand of all who hate us
to show mercy
and to our ancestors
and to remember his holy covenant
the oath he swore to our father Abraham
to rescue us
from the hand of our enemies
and to enable us to serve him
without fear and holiness
and righteousness
before him all our days
OK
這個祝福
是叫Zacharias Benedictus
我們首先看到
Next slide
他是filled with the Holy Spirit
他之前是啞了的
現在一可以說話
他就怎樣
他去祝福
祝福神
他不是祝福神
祝福Israel
祝福神的僕人
祝福神的人
OK
He's blessing God's people
他第一是說什麼
他說The past
然後他會說The present
然後他會說The future
The past, right?
The first thing he says is the past
神怎樣去祝福Israel
God has redeemed Israel
God has raised up
the horn of salvation
God has raised up the horn of salvation
然後他看什麼
Sorry
The present
He speaks to his own son John
My child
You will be a prophet for the Most High
You will go before the Lord
to prepare His way
他就唱John will become the one
who prepares the way for the Lord
所以首先他是說The past
The past is God has blessed Israel
God will redeem His people
第二
He speaks to the present
He speaks to John
John, you will have a very important role
to prepare the way for the people
然後第三
He looks forward
The sunrise from on high shall visit us
The light to those who sit in the darkness
In the shadow of death
To guide our feet
Into the way of peace
他說將來
這個救主會做什麼
他帶領神的光
去 overcome the darkness
OK
So we see from Zacharias Benedictus
that he is filled with the Holy Spirit
You can go home and read later
We don't have time to read all of it
He speaks of the past
What God has done
The present who John will become
And in the future
What God will do
That He will save His people
He will bring light into the darkness
He will redeem His people
And so we see that the Holy Spirit is active
The Holy Spirit is active
He was active in the past
He is active in the present
And He will be active in the future
To fulfill the plan of the Lord
OK
Now is the time for student story
Let's give a hand to Yarden
His name is Yarden
Yarden 你同我哋分享下
你個家庭嘅背景係點嘅
我個家庭背景呢
有啲怪嘅
我爸爸呢就係好信風水嘅
佢係乜嘢都係話係風水
所以有陣時我返完學之後呢
我會見到我成家嘅傢俬
乜嘢都搬曬
有陣時就瞓喺窗側邊
有陣時就瞓喺門側邊
有陣時瞓喺中間
係囉
跟住我個姨呢
就係好信佛嘅
不過呢
佢信極呢
都係有情緒問題
瞓唔到
要食嗰啲安眠藥
係囉
即係都冇乜幫助
你覺得
係囉
咁你自己
你個背景都好特別
每個禮拜返嚟
成間屋都唔同嘅
It's like a new house everyday
咁你點
你覺得神點帶領你去認識主耶穌呢
我係喺學校嗰度認識主耶穌
不過呢
我一兩年班已經信耶穌
我就冇做耶穌叫我做嘅嘢
跟住呢
不過呢
我大過啲呢
上中學嗰陣時
喺我哋學校啲gospel camp嗰度呢
就認識耶穌多啲
I see, very good
你哋係Christian school
So you have Christian teaching
And so that's how Jordan got to know Jesus
所以都好特別
因為你爸爸係信風水嘅
但係佢係帶領你去Christian Alliance International School
佢係咪覺得Christian Alliance International School個風水好好
所以佢帶領你去嗰度
係咪啲傢俬係咪好proper
啲窗係好大
係咪所以帶領你去嗰度
因為我以前上堂坐唔定
所以要我返CIS
Ok
上唔定
所以佢就send咗你去個Christian school
希望基督教可以幫到你
Ok, I see
When did you start to take God seriously
or what made you change to take God seriously
我係今年先開始take God seriously
我係喺今年嘅gospel camp
真係明白點解要信神
因為我以前信神
因為我驚死咗之後落地獄
哈哈哈哈
邊個講㗎
唔該
跟住不過我而家就明白
我而家信神係因為我想好似
同佢有一個親密嘅關係
有佢啲characteristics
Ok, become more like God
Yes, very good
Very good
So it's an amazing story
Right?
Just like Elizabeth and Mary
These were two unexpected households
Right?
That God would use
But Yarden was able to get to know Jesus
through the school
Even though his dad believes in feng shui
And he could have sent him to a Buddhist school
Right?
There's Buddhist schools in Hong Kong
But he didn't
And yet God through the Holy Spirit
Sent him to Christian Alliance International School
And that's how he got to know Jesus
So let's give a hand to Yarden for sharing today
Ok, thank you Yarden
Ok, so to summarize today
We see that the Holy Spirit is working
In the past, in the present and in the future
Advent is about waiting
Waiting for the Lord to come
And before they were waiting for a savior
Right?
They were waiting for Jesus to come again
The Messiah to save them from the Romans
From the Egyptians
From the Assyrians
From the Babylonians
They were always persecuted
And so they were waiting for a savior
And so just like they were waiting back then for a savior
Today we are also waiting
We are also waiting for Jesus to come again
To save this world from the disasters
From the wars
From the sin of this world
To one day make heaven and earth new again
We are also waiting today
And we need to believe in these three things
That the Holy Spirit is active today
He was active in the Bible time
And he's active now in our lives
He's active to help Yarden to know Jesus
And to bring him to church
He's active in your fellowships
In your discussion groups
He's active in your life today
And he's active in the future
To bringing Jesus to come again
To make everything new
And secondly, we see that the Holy Spirit
Aligns our hearts with God's heart
Right? Yarden said he wants to know Jesus
Because he wants to have the characteristics of Jesus
Love, goodness, peace, joy
All the fruits of the Spirit
And we need to align our heart to the Lord
By surrendering to his Holy Spirit
We need to surrender to the Holy Spirit
And what he's doing today
And lastly, as we align ourselves to the Holy Spirit
We will have an assembly of joy
We will have a community of joy
An explorer community of joy
And so that is the lesson that we learn
From the parents today
Mary, right?
Was filled with the Holy Spirit
And that created a joy
Joyful household
Mary aligned her life, her heart to the Lord
Humbled herself to the Lord
And so that brought about the Jesus
That saves us today
And lastly, Zachariah
Understood that God was active in the past
He's active in the present
And he's active in the future
God is working in our life, in our church
And we need to surrender to this Holy Spirit
The works of the Holy Spirit
As the band comes up
Let's take a moment right now
Let's just put out our hands
As the band comes up
Let's close our eyes
Let's bow down our heads
Close our eyes
And let us invite the Holy Spirit
Into our life
Let's close our eyes
We're done
Everybody close your eyes
Close your eyes
Let's stretch out our hands
And let's invite the Holy Spirit
Into our life
Take a moment to pray for yourself
That you would surrender yourself
To the Holy Spirit
Take a moment now
(音樂)
Everyone who has confessed Jesus to be Lord and Savior
Has been given the gift of the Holy Spirit
The seal of the Holy Spirit
As we see in the book of Ephesians
But whether the Holy Spirit
Is working in your life
It requires you to surrender to the Holy Spirit
If you're willing to surrender to the Holy Spirit
Say this prayer with me
Repeat after me
Dear God
I thank you for the Holy Spirit
Let's say it together
Ready? One, two, three
I thank you that the Holy Spirit
Has been working in the past
The present and the future
I now surrender my life to the Holy Spirit
May you help me to share your word
To those around me
To proclaim the good news of Jesus Christ
Fill me with your power
And your presence
In Jesus' name I pray
Amen
(字幕由 Amara.org 社群提供)